Okay, בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף daf is בבא מציעא מ',
Bava Metzia mem, בבא מציעא Bava Metzia 40, and we pick up
ל"ט ע"ב lamed tet amud bet about a third from the bottom,
מרי בר איסאק, Mari bar Isak, and our learning should be in
the זכות zechut of our חיילים וחיילות chayalim ve-chayalot and for the
prayer for the speedy return of the hostages and the speedy end
of the war. Okay, so we have had a whole long discussion
about this question about מורידים קרוב לנכסי שבוי, moridin karov lenichsei shavuy,
if you can have when somebody is overseas, might be dead, might
be captive, can you have a relative go into the property and
work the land and harvest it and so on, and also a
question about
נכסי קטן, nichsei katan, whether a קרוב karov can work in the
land of a קטן, katan, all of these were our discussions until
now. And now we pick up with the following story. So מרי
בר איסאק, Mari bar Isak, it
says, אתא ליה אחא מבי חוזאי, ata lei acha mibei Chuzai, a
brother came to him from בי חוזאי, Bei Chuzai, somebody claiming to
be his brother came from בי חוזאי. Bei Chuzai. אמר ליה פלוג
לי, amar lei plog li, and he said, yeah our father's dead
and I'm your brother and give me half of the estate. אמר
ליה, amar lei, he said back to him, לא ידענא לך, la
yadeina lach, I don't know who you are. אתא קמיה דרב חסדא,
ata kamey de-Rav Chisda, he came to רב חסדא. Rav Chisda. אמר
ליה שפיר קאמר לך, amar lei shapir ka'amar lach, רב חסדא Rav
Chisda said, you know what, it could be you are the brother
and it could be that he's not being dishonest with you, it
could be he genuinely doesn't recognize. That happens sometimes, שנאמר, shenemar, the
פסוק pasuk says, ויכר יוסף את אחיו והם לא הכירוהו, Vayaker Yosef
et echav vehem lo hikiruhu, Yosef recognized his brothers, they didn't recognize
him. How's that possible? מלמד שיצא בלא חתימת זקן ובא בחתימת זקן.
Melamed sheyatza belo chatimat zakan uva bechatimat zakan. It teaches you that
he left without a beard and when they came, he had a
beard on his face, so he wasn't recognizable to them. So maybe
he left when you were very young and he genuinely doesn't recognize
you. Also maybe he doesn't even know that he had a
brother, so maybe the father had a brother overseas he didn't know
about it. So he's not necessarily lying to you. Okay,
so if you take a look at תוספות, Tosafot, תוספות Tosafot says
that it's not that you needed that explanation
because it's not like let's say he says, no, no, no, he
only left a month ago from this place. So all of a
sudden we would believe a guy to claim that he was the
brother because everybody's believed to claim it's the brother? So obviously not.
So it just means though you can't come and say you're the
brother, you need to bring proof, but the fact that he's denying
it also doesn't mean that he is lying. Okay, so let's take
a look. מלמד ש, Melamed she, okay, so אמר ליה זיל אייתי
סהדי דאחוה את. amar lei zil aytei sahedi de-achuh at. So he
said look, you're claiming to be the brother, we don't know about
that, go bring evidence, go bring proof that you are the brother,
which is very reasonable. אמר ליה, amar lei, he said back to
him, אית לי סהדי ודחלי מיניה, it li sahedi u-dechali minei, I
have witnesses, but I'm afraid of this מרי בר איסאק, Mari bar
Isak, why? דגברא אלמא הוא, de-gavra alma hu, he's a very violent
man and the witnesses will come and they'll be afraid of repercussions
and they won't testify. So I can't really bring people to testify.
אמר ליה לדידיה, amar lei le-didei, so then he said to מרי,
Mari, so רב חסדא Rav Chisda said to מרי בר איסאק, Mari
bar Isak, זיל אנת אייתי סהדי דלאו אחוך הוא. zil ant aytei
sahedi de-lav achuch hu.
You go and bring witnesses that he's not your brother. Now it's
harder to disprove something. I mean, what are you going to do?
You're going to bring witnesses that are going to say what, that
they lived with the father, they were in the same town of
the father and they didn't know that the father had a child?
I mean, how do you know what the father was doing in
private? Are they going to say they knew where this guy grew
up? I mean, okay, I guess if they knew where he grew
up and he knew that he had a father, that he was
a two-parent
household and the father wasn't מרי בר איסאק's Mari bar Isak father,
you could presume that it's not a brother, but it's pretty hard
to prove a negative. But somehow you would bring enough evidence from
this person and from where he grew up that he was never
known to be the brother, he never claimed that this person was
his father, you bring proof that establishes the presumption at least that
he is not your brother. All right, so it says, אמר
ליה דינא הכי, amar lei dina hachi, is that the הלכה? halacha?
המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה, Hamotzi me-chavero alav ha-rayah, the one who's coming
to take out of somebody's hands, he has to bring the proof.
So this brother person claiming to be my brother, he has the
burden of proof to show that he is my brother. I don't
have to try to ward off all false claims and try to
disprove something,
clearly then people would constantly be making claims against his property. So
אמר ליה, amar lei, he said back to him, הכי דאינא לך
ולכל אלימי דחברך. hachi daina lach u-lechol alimei de-chavrach. Yes, this is
how I will judge you and all violent people like you. Yes,
because you cow witnesses into not testifying, I will use my discretion
and demand that you bring the evidence, which is pretty fascinating in
terms of the idea of what type of
discretion a judge has, number one. Number two, as תוספות Tosafot says,
this doesn't mean that anybody who is
a strong-armed person, all of a sudden he has to bring evidence
to defend claims against him.
but they're afraid. So because he was claiming to have witnesses, but
they're afraid, that
substantiated this guy's claim, gave a little more backing to it, and
therefore he turned it on this מרי בר איסק. Mari bar Isak.
I gotta tell you, it still doesn't make any sense, then people
will constantly be suing this מרי בר איסק Mari bar Isak and
claiming they have witnesses, but they can't come, and מרי בר איסק
Mari bar Isak will have to like disprove all of those false
claims. So, anyway, you have to understand what the exact circumstances were,
but that's what רב חסדא Rav Chisda was saying. You have to
bring the witnesses. All right, let's see what happens.
אמר ליה Amlei סוף סוף sof sof אתי סהדי ולא מסהדי. ati
sadi velo mesadi. He says, look, I'm gonna go ahead and bring
witnesses, and what's gonna happen and they won't testify? The phrase won't
testify is a little funny, but the point is, he's saying to
רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, if you think that I basically cow witnesses
into silence, what good is it going to do that I'm going
to bring
witnesses that will testify against what this claimant is saying? You're afraid
that I'm going to force people false witnesses to testify falsely? So
what good is it even going to do if I bring witnesses?
So רב חסדא Rav Chisda says back to him, אמר ליה Amralei
תרתי לא עבדי. tarti lo avdi. They won't do two things. Witnesses
might be cowed into silence, but I don't believe that witnesses are
going to actually actively testify falsely because they're afraid of you. So
if you can bring witnesses that testify that you're the brother, then
I will accept that and get rid of this claimant.
Okay, so let's take a look what happened. לסוף, Lesof, at the
end, אתו סהדי דאחוה הוא. asu sadi dehu hu. In the end,
actually, the witnesses that were claimed to exist all along to say
that this person was a brother actually were not cowed and actually
did come and testified that this person was the brother. So that
was a fascinating back and forth
and really interesting about how things could be reversed and the types
of ways in which this מרי בר איסק Mari bar Isak would
be exposed to all these claims, but at least in the end,
it genuinely was proved that this person was his brother. Okay, let's
see what happens. אמר ליה Amlei לפלוג לי נמי מפרדיסאי ובוסתנאי דשתל.
liflog li nami mipardisai uvestinai deshatal. So he said, so now this
brother said to מרי בר איסק, Mari bar Isak, okay, I get
half of the property. I also want half of the orchards and
the
gardens that you planted when you thought it was all yours, you
invested a lot of money, manure
and trees
and bulbs and all this stuff and effort, and you planted these
gardens
and these vineyards
and orchards, and now I get half of
this. דשתל Deshatal אמר ליה amlei שפיר
קאמר לך. shapir kama lakh. So רב חסדא Rav Chisda said to
this מרי בר איסק, Mari bar Isak, he has a good claim.
On the face of it it doesn't look like a good claim.
מרי בר איסק Mari bar Isak put in all of this expenses
and effort, why should this guy benefit to the improvements that he
made? So he says, no, he made a good claim. Why? דתנן,
Detnan, we taught in the משנה, Mishnah, הניח בנים גדולים וקטנים והשביחו
גדולים את הנכסים השביחו לאמצע. hiniach banim gedolim uketanim vehishpichu gedolim es
hanechasim hishpichu le'emtsa. If somebody dies and leaves behind children, and some
are adults and some are children, and some are under age, and
the adult children go ahead and they improve the value of the
property, exactly something like this, they plant, they harvest, they hoe, then
that is equally divided, the improvement goes to the middle, meaning it's
jointly shared. So even the underage children who did not work the
land benefit from the improvement that the heirs made. So here too,
you're both heirs. You, מרי בר איסק, Mari bar Isak, made these
improvements, everybody benefits. Now there's obviously a big difference between these cases,
which we'll see in a minute, but let's see how this wraps
up. וכן אמר רבא השביחו לאמצע. Vechen amar Rava hishpichu le'emtsa. And
רבא Rava similarly said that when improvements are made, this is the
גמרא Gemara talking, not רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, because רבא Rava came
after רב חסדא. Rav Chisda. Okay, that the benefit goes to the
middle. אמר ליה אביי, Amlei Abaye, but when רבא Rava said this,
then אביי Abaye challenged back, this is how תוספות Tosfos explains it,
מי דמי? mi dami? How can you compare them, those two cases?
התם Hasam גדולים גבי קטנים ידעי וקמחלי. gedolim gabei ketanim yadi vekamachli.
If you have adult children
and minor children, when the adult children are choosing to work the
property, they know of the existence of the minor children and they
are waiving their rights. They're basically saying we're doing this, if they
didn't stipulate otherwise, it's assumed to be that they're doing it on
behalf of all of the heirs. They're aware of them, they're not
stipulating otherwise, so they're waiving their rights that all of the benefit
should be there. הכא מי ידעי דאיתך? Hacha mi yadi delitkho?
But here, he didn't, מרי בר איסק Mari bar Isak didn't know
about this brother. So how could we say that מרי בר איסק's
Mari bar Isak efforts should be shared by this brother, why does
this brother have right to the improvements that מרי בר איסק Mari
bar Isak made in the property?
איגגל מילתא. Igagal milsa. to רבי, Rebbe, oh, excuse me, not to
רבי, Rebbe, to רבי אמי, Rabbi Ami, excuse me, to רבי אמי.
Rabbi Ami. אמר להו גדולה מזו אמרו שמין להן כאריס. Amar lehu
gedola mizu amru shamin lahen ke-aris.
So they even said something bigger than this, meaning that when you
actually had the case of the of somebody who goes down, and
going back to our case before about the relative who goes down
to the, you know, who works the fields of the שבוי, shavuy,
of the person that's missing and absent, it says that he's able
to get paid like a שמין להן כאריס, shamin lahen ke-aris, a
half, a third, a quarter. He gets back for his efforts, and
there's even an opinion, you know, whole debate of רש"י ותוספות Rashi
and Tosafot whether he even gets to, if the stuff reaches harvest,
whether he gets to eat the actual produce itself. But regardless, he
minimally gets paid back for the effort and the expenses. So, if
that's what they said, so when he is actually working somebody else's
field, שמין להן כאריס השתא דידיה לא יהבינן ליה? shamin lahen ke-aris
hashta didei lo yavinan lei?
His own stuff we wouldn't give him? When he worked this, he
thought it was his own. He certainly should be entitled, even if
we split it and give half and so on, because it turned
out it was the brother's, you know, half of it was the
brother's, but he should at least be entitled to getting paid for
his efforts on what he did on that other half, like an
אריס. aris. אהדרוה הא לקמיה דרב חסדא. Adruha ha lekamei deRav Chisda.
So the case came back to רב חסדא. Rav Chisda. אמר להו
מי דמי? Amar lehu mi dami? So they said, "Hey, רב חסדא,
Rav Chisda, the רבי אמי Rabbi Ami says, you know, he should
at least be entitled to, to like a שמין להן כאריס shamin
lahen ke-aris in that half." So רב חסדא Rav Chisda said, "How
can you compare the case? התם ברשות נחית הכא לא ברשות נחית."
Hatam birshut nachis hacha lav birshut nachis.
So in that case, the case of the קרוב לנכסי שבוי, karov
lenichsei shavuy, he had permission, meaning that,
you know, בית דין Beit Din allowed him to do it. He
had license to do it. It even says before that it was
a תקנה, takana, you know, that he, that they made. So therefore,
because they intentionally wanted the field to be worked and he was
intentionally doing it and knowing the, you know, the parameters, he's entitled
to the benefits like a שמין להן כאריס. shamin lahen ke-aris. Here,
this guy didn't have any license from בית דין. Beit Din. He
thought it was his own. Now, it might be he thought it
was his own, but really he's going to be entitled to nothing?
But okay, that's what he says.
ועוד קטן הוא. Ve-od katan hu. ואמרינן קרוב לנכסי קטן. Ve-amrinan karov
lenichsei katan. And not only that, in the end what this guy,
this brother, remember it said before that he didn't have a beard?
So when מרי בר איסק Mari Bar Isak worked the field, this
brother was still a minor, and therefore it would be a case
of a קרוב karov working in the field of a קטן katan
that's not around, of a minor relative that's not around, and we
don't allow that. So not only did he not have an explicit
license from the בית דין, Beit Din, he was operating in a
type of a scenario in which we would disapprove had we known
about it. Now of course, מרי בר איסק Mari Bar Isak didn't
do anything wrong; he thought it was all his property. But that's
the reason, this is the way that רב חסדא Rav Chisda wants
to say he's not entitled to even get any of his efforts
and his expenses back. It seems רב חסדא Rav Chisda really had
a thing for this מרי בר איסק. Mari Bar Isak. So let's
take a look.
אהדרוה לקמיה דרבי אמי. Adruha lekamei deRabbi Ami. So they went back
and reported to רבי אמי Rabbi Ami that he was a קטן
katan and therefore, you know, this brother, and therefore מרי בר איסק
Mari Bar Isak should not be entitled to his efforts.
אמר להו לא שמו קמיה דקטן הוא. Amar lehu lo simu kamei
de-katan hu. When you told me the story, you didn't tell me
this missing piece of information. That was a very important piece of
information. If I had known that he was a קטן, katan, then
I would have agreed that מרי בר איסק Mari Bar Isak is
not entitled to his efforts. Okay, so this is a practical application
of things we had talked about of קרוב לנכסי שבוי, karov lenichsei
shavuy, and whether somebody who works somebody else's field is entitled to
their effort. Normally we would assume that they would be, like an
אריס, aris, you know, some degree of compensation. But here in this
case of מרי בר איסק, Mari Bar Isak, they wanted to deny
it to him. It seems obviously this guy was a strongman, but
the argument and they wanted to turn around who needed to bring
the witnesses. And the argument that was made was that first of
all was that if one of the heirs works the property, everybody
shares it. And the other is that it turned out that he
was a קרוב לנכסי קטן, karov lenichsei katan, and therefore, you know,
was not entitled to getting compensated for his effort. One wonders if
that means even like minimally for his expenses, but certainly not a
significant return on his effort. Okay, that is the end of that
whole סוגיא sugya about קרוב לנכסי שבוי. karov lenichsei shavuy. Now we
turn to the next משנה. Mishnah. המפקיד פירות אצל חבירו הרי זה
יוציא לו חסרונות לחטין
ולאורז תשעה חצי קבין. Hamafkid peirot etzel chaveiro harei zeh yotzi lo
cheshronot lachitin ule-orez tisha chatzi kabin. So if somebody, you know, entrusts
various types of fruit or grain to his friend to watch, and
the גמרא Gemara is going to say that the case is that
the person mixed this up with his other grain, you know, just
put it in the granary.
that actually you don't have to give back the full amount you
received because we assume that a certain
amount got eaten away, whether it's by rats or whether it's by
the husks falling off, but other types of mold or other things,
so actually you can give back a smaller amount because that amount
that was given to you would actually have shrunk. How much do
we assume? Now the גמרא's Gemara going to ask why not just
do it proportional to how much all of his grain shrunk. We'll
worry about that. But how much do we have to assume that
it shrunk? So it said if it is wheat and rice, so
it's nine half קבין kabin to a כור. kor. Now what that
comes to is there are thirty סאה se'ah in a כור kor
and there are six קב kav to a סאה. se'ah. So there
are 180 קב kav to a כור. kor. So if this were
nine קבין kabin to a כור, kor, so that would be 5%,
right? 18 is 10%. So now divide it by two again because
it's nine half קבין kabin it's 2.5%. Okay,
2.5%. לשעורין ולדוחן Lise'orin uledochen for barley and דוחן dochen which is
millet, don't know exactly what that is,
תשעה קבין לכור tish'ah kabin lekor nine קבין kabin to a כור
kor which is 5%. לכוסמין ולזרע פשתן Likosmin ulezera pishtan for כוסמין
kosmin which is spelt and for flaxseed, I was just asked a
question about flaxseed and קטניות, kitniyot, לזרע פשתן lezera pishtan שלוש סאין
לכור shalosh se'in lekor three סאה se'ah to a כור kor that's
10%. Remember thirty סאה se'ah to a כור. kor. הכל לפי המידה
והכל לפי הזמן. Hakol lefi hamidah vehakol lefi hazman. It all based
on this is if you had a כור's kor worth, but it's
all proportional. If you have ten כור's kor worth, multiply by ten.
This is the amount it loses per year. If it was three
years, multiply by three. Okay. אמר רבי יוחנן בן נורי וכי מה
אכפת להן לעכברין והלא אוכלות בין מהרבה ובין מקמעא. Amar Rabbi Yochanan
ben Nuri vechi mah ichpas lahen le'achbarin vehalo ochlot bein meharbeh uvein
mikim'a. And Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri said, what do the rats care
about if what's being lost is what a rat eats, then the
rats don't eat proportional to the amount of food that there is
there, they're going to eat the same amount.
אלא אינו מוציא לו חסרונות אלא לכור אחד בלבד. ela eino motzi
lo chesronot ela lekor echad bilvad. The amount you deduct is the
amount you would deduct for one כור. kor. Now תוספות Tosafot says
obviously if it was less than a כור kor that was stored
with him, it would be proportional. But once it hits a כור,
kor, whatever the amounts here are, 2.5%, 5%, 10%, he thinks nine
קב, kav, nine half קבין, kabin, he thinks that's the total amount
that the rats will eat, and even if there's ten times as
much grain, it's not going to lose more than that nine קב
kav or whatever it would be. We'll see in the גמרא Gemara
what the חכמים Chachamim respond back. רבי יהודה אומר אם הייתה מידה
מרובה אינו מוציא לו חסרונות מפני שמותירות. Rabbi Yehuda omer im hayetah
midah merubah eino motzi lo chesronot mipnei shemosirot. If it was a
very large amount, the גמרא's Gemara going to say ten כור, kor,
then you don't return anything because they expand. This means that if
the grain was given at the dry season and returned in the
wet season, so the moisture whatever makes the grain expand, so actually
if you give back the same measure, you measure out this gallon
or whatever, it'll be less grain in it in the wet season
because the grain will be bigger than it was in the dry
season. So that difference, the expanded sort of volume is going to
mean that if you're giving back in the wet season you give
back the same measure you got and the difference between the actual
amount of grain, that expands the difference. So let's say the difference
was nine whatever, 5%. So what he's saying is you don't have
to give 5% more grain if you're giving back in the rainy
season because the grain would have expanded 5%. So what you're giving
back is already 5% less than what you received. Again, one wonders
does it exactly work to the proportion said before. Anyway, let's see
what the גמרא Gemara says. אורז
טובא חסר. Orez tuva chasar. The גמרא Gemara says rice, rice is
a lot more than 2.5% over a year. אמר רבה בר בר
חנה אמר רבי יוחנן באורז קלוף שנו. Amar Rabbah bar bar Chana
amar Rabbi Yochanan be'orez kaluf shanu. We're talking about peeled rice. Okay,
and that is this lesser amount. Apparently if it's not peeled the
shells fall off and it the amount the volume decreases even more.
אמר רבי יוחנן אמר רבי חייא זרע פשתן בגבעולין שנו. Amar Rabbi
Yochanan amar Rabbi Chiya zera pishtan begiv'olin shanu. לכוסמין ולזרע פשתן ג'
סאין לכור. Likosmin ulezera pishtan gimmel se'in lekor. So for flaxseed and
for כוסמין kosmin which I'm forgetting again what that was, whatever it
is, anyway let me look it up, כוסמין kosmin is
spelt. That is okay, that is nine קב kav for the כור,
kor, שלוש סאין לכור, shalosh se'in lekor, three, 10%. Three סאין se'in
for the כור. kor. אמר רבי יוחנן אמר רבי חייא זרע פשתן
בגבעולין שנו. Amar Rabbi Yochanan amar Rabbi Chiya zera pishtan begiv'olin shanu.
Here why it's so much, 10%, we're talking about flaxseeds that are
in the husks and that's why they lose a lot because the
husks crush. tumble and fall away. תניא נמי הכי, tanya nami hachi,
it was taught similarly, לכוסמין ולזרע פשתן בגבעולין ולאורז
שאינו קלוף le'kusmin u'le'zera pishtan be'givolin u'le'orez she'eino kaluf
and rice that is not peeled, for both whether it's flaxseed that's
unpeeled or rice that's unpeeled, שלשה סאין לכור, shlosha se'in le'kor, that's
ten percent. So it's a little funny that the Mishnah was talking
about peeled rice and unpeeled flaxseed, but anyway the Baraita, Tosafot discusses
why that might be, but anyway the Baraita makes it clear that
if they're both unpeeled it's ten percent, the peel, the husks will
crumble or fall off, and if they're unpeeled it is a much
lesser amount. Okay. הכל לפי המדה. hakol lefi hamidah. תנא כן לכל
כור וכור וכן לכל שנה ושנה. tana ken le'chol kor ve'kor ve'chen
le'chol shanah ve'shanah. You just multiply by the number of kors and
by the number of years. אמר רבי יוחנן בן נורי, amar Rabbi
Yochanan ben Nuri, Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri says the rats don't eat
a proportional amount, the rats eat a fixed amount. תניא אמרו לו
לרבי יוחנן, tanya amru lo le'Rabbi Yochanan, they said to Rabbi Yochanan,
הרבה אובדות מהן הרבה מתפזרות מהן. harbeh ovdot mehen harbeh mitpazrot mehen.
It's not just about rats. You know, things get lost, some of
the stuff crumbles, some of it spreads away. So things can lose
some of their volume having nothing to do with rats and that
is proportional to the amount of grain that you have. Now Tosafot
quotes a very funny Yerushalmi. וכי מה איכפת להו לעכברים? ve'chi mah
ichpat lehu le'achbarim? Tosafot says like this, וטעמייהו דרבנן מפרש בירושלמי הני
עכברים רשיעי נינהו. ve'tama'yeihu de'Rabbanan meforash be'Yerushalmi hanei achbarim rishi'ei ninhu. These
rats are rasha'im. כד חמן עיבור לא מסתייעו דאכלי אלא קרו לחבריהון
דאכלין עמהון. kad chamyan ibur lo mistaye'u de'achli ela karun le'chavreihon de'achlin
imehon. When they see grain, it's not enough that they eat,
but they call their friends to eat with them. So they basically
say yes, when there's a lot of food, the word gets out
and more does get eaten than when there is less food. Okay,
I cannot testify to that one way or the other. Back to
anyway it's a different answer than our Gemara gave. Back to the
Gemara.
Okay. תנו רבנן. tanu Rabbanan. We taught in a Baraita. במה דברים
אמורים שעירב מפירותיו. bamah devarim amurim she'eirev mi'peirotav. Why do you have
to figure out how much the volume would have shrunk? Just give
him back what he gave you. So it says okay, the case
of the Mishnah is that it's mixed up with your own grain
and therefore you have to figure out what the proportion is because
you don't have the grain itself to give back. So the Gemara
says, אבל ייחד לו קרן זוית. aval yichad lo keren zavit. Oh,
let's just finish the end. But if it's in a particular location,
אומר לו הרי שלך לפניך. omer lo harei shelcha lefanecha. He gives
them back: this is yours, I didn't touch it. So now the
Gemara says, וכי עירבו עם פירותיו מאי הוי? ve'chi eirvo im peirotav
mai havei? And if he mixed them up with his own grain,
so what? Big deal. לחזי לדידיה כמה הויין. lechze'i ledideih kamah havyan.
Not big deal, I shouldn't have said. Anyway, but why do you
have to use these amounts in the Mishnah? If he mixed it
up with his own grain, just see how much the volume of
his own grain went down and everything went down proportionally. So just
actually get some empirical, you know, data here. Why are you basing
it on these amounts? So the Gemara says, במיסתפק מהן. be'mistapek mehen.
No, because he's actually been eating from his grain, so therefore he
doesn't know how much his grain has gone down. So the Gemara
says, ולחזי כמה איסתפק. ve'lechze'i kamah istapak. Why doesn't he see how
many bags did he take out, how much is left now, and
do all the math? So the Gemara says, דלא ידעי כמה איסתפק.
dela yada'ei kamah istapak. He doesn't know. He's been regularly taking grain,
you know, or apples or whatever it is from where it's being
stored. He's not paying attention to how much. He has no way
of measuring for his own stuff how much it decreased in volume.
So that's why you need these measures. Okay.
רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, אם היתה. im hayta. Rabbi Yehuda
said that you don't need, if you're giving it back in the
rainy season, that wasn't in the Mishnah but that's what the Gemara
is going to say, you don't have to deduct, you know, you
don't have to give back a smaller volume, you're already giving back
less because the stuff has now expanded.
כמה מידה מרובה? kamah midah merubah? How much is a big amount?
אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן עשרה כורין. amar Rabbah
bar bar Chanah amar Rabbi Yochanan asarah korin. Ten kor. תניא נמי
הכי כמה מידה מרובה עשרה כורין. tanya nami hachi kamah midah merubah
asarah korin. Okay, which raises a question. Why do you need there
to be a lot? I mean, if there's less, the stuff doesn't
expand? But okay. So Rashi says that the reason that it has
to be a lot is because, going back to sort of the
point before about Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri, that the rats, you know,
if you have a huge amount, the rats are only going to
eat a tiny percentage of it. They can only eat so many.
It's not going to be proportional. So once you get to a
huge amount, it's not going to be proportional; it's only going to
be a small depreciation or, you know, shrinking in volume, and that
will be made up by the expanding. But if it's a smaller
amount, then the stuff that will be eaten will be a larger
percentage of it and it won't be made up by the expanding.
Okay.
תני תנא קמיה דרב נחמן. tani tana kameih de'Rav Nachman. A Tanna
taught in front of Rav Nachman.
במה דברים אמורים שמדדו מתוך גורנו והחזירו מתוך גורנו.
bamah devarim amurim she'madadu mi'toch
gorno ve'hechziro mi'toch gorno. אבל מדדו מתוך גורנו והחזירו מתוך ביתו אינו
יוצא לו חסרונות מפני שמוגירות. aval madadu mi'toch gorno ve'hechziro mi'toch beito
einu yotze lo chisronot mipnei she'mogirot. All right. So this is, you
know, a similar idea that it expands, but it says it the
following way. When do you go by these quantities of, you know,
giving back a smaller volume? When you measured it out in the
granary and you gave it back in the granary. But if you
measured out in the granary and gave it back in the home...
measured it out in the granary but if he gave it to
you with measuring it in the granary and you returned it by
measuring it in the house, then you don't have to make it
up you're already giving him back. Now,
why should it matter that it expands in the house as opposed
to expands in the granary? So really the point here is not
expansion, but it's really the fact that, you know, they used much
bigger measuring vessels in the granary you're dealing with much larger volumes
than in the home, than in the kitchen. So the home measuring
even presumably if they're supposed to, you know, things that might be
even called the same, a סאה Seah and a קב Kav or
whatever it would be, you know, somehow the measurements that you use
at the home are smaller measurements. So he's saying if the guy
measured out a קב Kav in the granary and you're giving him
a קב Kav at home, you're already giving him less. So you
don't have so you don't have to worry about the things in
the משנה. Mishna. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: אמר ליה
וכי בשופתני עסקינן? Amar lei vechi b'shuftani askinan? דייהבי בכלי רבא ושקלי
בכלי זוטא? De'yahavi b'keli raba v'shakli b'keli zuta? Are we talking about
idiots? That they give their grain in big measures and they take
it back in small measures? Nobody would take back using the house
measures for the stuff that they gave in the, you know, in
the granary with the granary measures.
So the גמרא Gemara says so he said back to him, דילמא
בימות הגורן קאמרת? Dilma biyemos hagoren kaamart? Maybe you didn't mean, and
this is what I was referring to before, maybe you didn't mean
in the granary, you meant during the time of the granary. Okay?
במדרעום B'madraom שמאדד לו בימות הגורן והחזיר לו בימות הגורן. Shemadad lo
biyemos hagoren vehachzir lo biyemos hagoren. When is it that you give
back less because some of it got, you know, some of the
volume shrunk because of the rats or whatever? When you measured it
out in the dry season and gave it back in the dry
season. That's called the granary season. Then it is the same volume.
אבל מדד לו בימות הגורן והחזיר לו בימות הגשמים. Aval madad lo
biyemos hagoren vehachzir lo biyemos hageshamim. If if it was measured out
and deposited when it was the dry season and given back in
the rainy season, now the same amount of grain takes up more
volume. And therefore, you know, you give back the even giving back
the same amount you was give you were given is giving less.
So you don't give back the less of the משנה, Mishna, the
same measure is really less cause it's the cause it's expanded because
of volume.
Okay. והחזיר לו בימות הגשמים אין מוציא לו חסרון מפני שמותירות. Vehachzir
lo biyemos hageshamim ein motzi lo chisaron mipney shemosiros. Fine, so that's
the explanation of the משנה. Mishna. אמר ליה רב פפא לאביי. Amar
lei Rav Papa l'Abaye. So Rav Papa said to Abaye, אם כן
לפקע כדא? Im kein lifka kada? So if that's true that grain
really expands in the rainy season, why if you have grain that's
filled up into a like a jug, why doesn't the jug burst
because of the expanding grain?
So הוה עובדא ופקע כדא. Hava uvda upaka kada. So one answer
is yes, that does happen sometimes. You know, you're supposed to leave
a little space for it to expand and if you don't leave
a little expansion, then maybe the jar will break.
אי בעית אימא משום איצצא. I bayis eima mishum itzitza. Or maybe
it doesn't expand if it's all compressed. It doesn't have room to
expand. But if it's not compressed, then actually it will expand. I
really cannot tell you which of these various explanations are correct. Okay,
let's see the next משנה. Mishna. יוציא לו שתות ליין. Yotzi lo
shtus leyayin. Similar to a concern here about, you know, if the
guy gave you x gallons, how much do you give back? So
it says that for wine you deduct a sixth. That's a lot.
That's like 16 percent. Okay?
Why? Because the the what do you call it the the jugs
absorb a sixth of the wine. So if the guy gave you,
you know, stuff in let's say a six-gallon jug, then when he
came back, if you had the same jug, then you would open
it up and there would only be five gallons of wine because
one-sixth of it would be absorbed in the jug. So if you
know the jug that he gave you, you know, that would happen
if it was pottery and porous. So if you knew the jug
that he gave you, so you would give him back the jug
and it would be whatever it would be. But if you mixed
it up with your jugs and you don't know, then you are
to assume that a sixth gets absorbed into it and you only
have to give him back five gallons of wine. One wonders why
they did not make better jugs, you know, or what if a
jug was old and already had absorbed wine in it? We'll see
some of that in the גמרא. Gemara. Okay. רבי יהודה אומר חומש.
Rabbi Yehuda omer chomesh. Not a sixth, a fifth. יוציא
לו. Yotzi lo. חומש Chomesh period. יוציא לו שלושה לוגין שמן למאה.
Yotzi lo shlosha lugin shemen l'me'ah. Now, if the person gives you
oil, then oil also will get absorbed into the pottery jug, so
you should take deduct three לוג Log of oil for every hundred.
So three percent, a much smaller amount. לוג ומחצה שמרים ולוג ומחצה
בלע. Log u'mechtza shemarim v'log u'mechtza bala. And here only a לוג
Log and a half gets absorbed into the jug, so one and
a half percent as opposed to 16 percent by the wine. And
one and a half is the lees that settle at the bottom
of the jug. So therefore, again, if you know the jug he
gave you, give him back the jug you gave you. If he
doesn't, you're going to give him back wine that from the top
that doesn't have the lees. So that will be, you have to
deduct that percentage if you had his wine. If I'm not wine,
excuse me, if you had his oil, then one and a half
percent would be he wouldn't be getting back because it would be
absorbed in the walls and one and a half would be the
lees at the bottom. So you're giving him back pure oil, so
you deduct 3 percent.
Okay.
לוג מחצא שמנא לוג מחצא בלא. Loga mechatza shamna loga mechatza bela.
אם היה שמן מזוקק אינה יוצי לא שמרים. Im haya shemen mezukak
eina yotzi lo shemarim. If he entrusted you with, you know, pure
oil that had already been the lees had been removed, then you
only deduct one and a half percent. You don't deduct the amount
for the, you know, for the, for the skins. אם היו קנקנין
ישנים, Im hayu kankanin yeshanim,
and if they were old jugs that had already absorbed oil, so
they couldn't absorb anymore, so then אינה יוצי לא בלא. Eina yotzi
lo bela. Then you don't deduct the amount that was absorbed, because
if he gave it to you in old jugs, nothing would have
been lost by absorption. רבי יהודה אומר אף המוכר שמן מזוקק לחבייר
כל ימות השנה הרי זה מקבל עליו לוג מחצא שמרים למאה. Rabbi
Yehuda omer af hamocher shemen mezukak lechaver kol yemot hashana harei ze
mekabel alav log mechatza shemarim leme'a. Even somebody who sells pure oil
to his friend at any time of the year, he has to
accept upon himself one and a half percent of, you know, of
like, of skins, of lees for every hundred units. Now, what does
this mean? So, we will see that
in
the גמרא Gemara that,
hold
on, I'm sorry. So what this means is that if somebody says
I'm going to sell you a barrel of oil, and you say
how much is it, it's ten dollars, great, and then I'm going
to then, you're going to come and, you know, every
throughout the year and I'll be providing you pure oil from that
barrel, that in the end what I'm going to give you is
I'm going to give you 98 and a half percent, you know,
of the barrel, because one and a half percent we will assume
will be the dross and the lees. So you have bought a
barrel with the dross, you've bought like the unrefined, and I deliver
the refined, so I get to deduct one and a half percent.
Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. ולא פליגי, Velo pligi,
says the גמרא, Gemara, the difference of a sixth and a fifth
are not really debating. מר כי אתריה ומר כי אתריה. Mar ki
atreh umar ki atreh. Each one goes according to his place. באתרא
דמר חפו בקירי, Be'atra demar chapu bekeri, in the place of the
one who said a sixth, the תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, they, they,
you know, coat the barrel with, with wax, ולא מייץ טפי, Velo
mayitz tfei, it doesn't suck up too much, it doesn't absorb so
much, only a sixth. Seems a lot to me. באתרא דמר חפו
בכופרא, Be'atra demar chapu bechufra, in the place of רב יהודה, Rav
Yehuda, they use pitch, ומייץ טפי, Umayitz tfei, and that absorbs more
and that's a fifth. איבעית אימא, Ibayit eima, if you want I
could you could say משום גרגשתא. Mishum gargishta. It is because of
the actual dirt that's used to make the jugs. In one place
it's more absorbent than the other. הא מייץ טפי והא לא מייץ
טפי, Ha mayitz tfei veha lo mayitz tfei, one place it more
is more absorbent than the other. באתרא דרב יהודה רמו ארבעין ותמני
כוזא בדנא. Be'atra deRav Yehuda ramu arba'in vetamni kuza bedana. Now, in
the place of רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, not רבי יהודה Rebi Yehuda
of the משנה, Mishnah, they, they, they had 48 of a particular
unit that would fill a barrel, a כוזא kuza that would fill
a barrel of wine. Okay. אזל
דנא בשישא זוזי. Azal dana beshisha zuzei. Now, a whole barrel went
for six זוז. zuz. פרש רב יהודה שישא שישא בזוזא. Parash Rav
Yehuda shisha shisha bezuza. So רב יהודה Rav Yehuda went and he
sold them six כוזא kuza for a זוז. zuz. So, the
barrel with 48 units went for six זוז. zuz. Okay. So, he
is now selling every six of those units for six זוז. zuz.
So how many six units how many units of six are there
in this barrel of 48? There are eight. So he is selling
six כוזא kuza for a זוז. zuz. It's a little hard to
say that. Anyway, so he bought the barrel for six, it had
48 units, he sold a זוז zuz for every six units, so
he's going to get eight for the barrel. Okay, שישא שישא בזוזא.
shisha shisha bezuza. Now, top of מ' עמוד ב'. Mem amud bet.
דל תלתין ושישא בשישא. Dal tlatin veshisha beshisha. Okay, so, so 36
for the first six units that he sell for the first 36
units that he sells he gets six זוז, zuz, he gets his
money back. פשלו ליה תריסר, Pashlu leh treisar, and now he's got
twelve more units that are profit. So that's going to be two
extra זוז zuz profit, the two זוז zuz will be the profit.
דל תמניא שיתותא. Dal tamanya shituta. Now, remember we said that wine
it absorbs a sixth. So actually, if it started with 48 units,
then a sixth of that is eight, so eight will be absorbed
into the barrel of the wine. So he's really only going to
have four more units left to sell. Okay, not as big of
a profit as we thought. פשלו ליה ארבע, Pashlu leh arba, so
he's left with four units left to sell, which is two-thirds of
a זוז. zuz. Fine. ואמר שמואל, v'amar Shmuel, now the גמרא Gemara
says, one minute, didn't שמואל Shmuel say המשתכר אל ישתכר יותר על
שתות, hamishtaker al yistaker yoter al shtut,
that if somebody is selling, and רש״י Rashi importantly says, selling something
that is considered to be a staple, they wanted to control the
prices, so they said you cannot get more of a profit than
a sixth of what you're buying it for. So they put limits,
you know, price control. So he bought this for six,
and his profit therefore he should have been able to get, שמואל
Shmuel would have allowed him to get a whole one unit profit,
a whole one זוז zuz profit, one-sixth, but he only got two-thirds
of a זוז zuz profit, right? Four units and six to a
זוז, zuz, it was two-thirds. So why? תוספות Tosafot says, presumably he
could have charged more, I don't know why we're assuming that, so
why didn't he charge more in order that he could get the
full profit that he was allowed? So the גמרא Gemara says, איכא
גופא ושמריא. ika gufa v'shmarya. So the גמרא Gemara says, no, no,
no, he did make a bigger profit. Why? He got the two-thirds
extra of a זוז zuz that he was able to sell because
of the extra wine, but when he bought it, he didn't just
buy the wine, he also bought the
barrel, okay, and he also gets the, you know, the lees, the
dross at the bottom. So he actually winds up getting two-thirds of
a זוז zuz profit for selling the extra wine that didn't get
absorbed, and the cost of the barrel and the cost of the
lees at the bottom. So that's a nice profit. So the גמרא
Gemara says, אי הכי נפיש ליה טפי. ee hachi nafish leh tefay.
So the גמרא Gemara says, wait, now we got a problem, now
he's making more than a sixth profit. So the גמרא Gemara says,
no, נפיש ליה טפי משתות, nafish leh tefay mishtut, more than the
sixth, says no, איכא טירחא ודמי
ברזינתא. ika tircha v'dmei barzinayta. No, no, no, he's entitled to get
money for his effort, for his labor, and for, like, ברזינתא barzinayta
is a question of what it means, but let's say it means,
you know, the skill of putting in the spigot. So this idea
that he can only get a sixth, that's beyond reimbursed for his
labor and expenses. So beyond his labor and expenses, he can get
a sixth profit. So this person, so here he was getting more
than a sixth profit, some of it went to his labor and
expenses, and beyond that, he was within the limits that שמואל Shmuel
set. Okay, we will end here for now.